On September 7, 1991, the costliest hailstorm in Canadian history hit Calgary’s southern suburbs.
1991年9月7日，加拿大历史上损失最惨重的一场雹暴袭击了卡尔加里南部的郊区。
As a result, since 1996 a group of insurance companies have spent about $2 million per year on the Alberta Hail Suppression Project.
因此，自1996年以来，一批保险公司每年在“艾伯塔防雹项目”上花费约200万美元。
Airplanes seed threatening storm cells with a chemical to make small ice crystals fall as rain before they can grow into dangerous hailstones.
飞机向有威胁的风暴单体播撒一种化学物质，使小冰晶在长成危险的冰雹之前就以雨的形式落下。
But farmers in east-central Alberta — downwind of the hail project flights — worry that precious moisture is being stolen from their thirsty land by the cloud seeding.
但是，艾伯塔省中东部的农民——他们正处在防雹项目飞行航线的下风处——担心播云正在偷走他们干渴土地上的宝贵水分。
Norman Stienwand, who farms in that area, has been addressing public meetings on this issue for years.
诺曼·斯廷万德在那个地区务农，多年来一直就这个问题在公众集会上发表讲话。
“Basically, the provincial government is letting the insurance companies protect the Calgary-Edmonton urban area from hail,” Mr. Stienwand says, “but they’re increasing drought risk as far east as Saskatchewan.”
“说白了，省政府是在让保险公司保护卡尔加里—埃德蒙顿城区免遭冰雹袭击，”斯廷万德先生说，“但他们却在加大干旱风险，波及范围向东远至萨斯喀彻温省。”
The Alberta hail project is managed by Terry Krauss, a cloud physicist who works for Weather Modification Inc. of Fargo, North Dakota.
艾伯塔防雹项目由特里·克劳斯管理，他是一位云物理学家，就职于北达科他州法戈市的天气调控公司。
“We affect only a very small percentage of the total moisture in the air, so we cannot be causing drought,” Dr. Krauss says.
“我们影响的只是空气中水分总量的极小一部分，所以我们不可能导致干旱，”克劳斯博士说。
“In fact, we may be helping increase the moisture downwind by creating wetter ground.”
“事实上，我们让地面变得更湿润，这可能正有助于增加下风处的水分。”
One doubter about the safety of cloud seeding is Chuck Doswell, a research scientist who just retired from the University of Oklahoma.
对播云安全性持怀疑态度的人当中，有一位是查克·多斯韦尔，他是一名刚从俄克拉何马大学退休的研究科学家。
“In 1999, I personally saw significant tornadoes form from a seeded storm cell in Kansas,” Dr. Doswell says.
“1999年，我亲眼看到堪萨斯州一个播撒过催化剂的风暴单体中形成了强龙卷风，”多斯韦尔博士说。
“Does cloud seeding create killer storms or reduce moisture downwind?
“播云会不会引发致命的风暴，或者减少下风处的水分？
No one really knows, of course, but the seeding goes on.”
当然，谁也说不清，但播云仍在继续。”
Given the degree of doubt, Mr. Stienwand suggests, “it would be wise to stop cloud seeding.”
鉴于疑虑如此之大，斯廷万德先生建议：“停止播云会是明智之举。”
In practice, doubt has had the opposite effect.
实际上，疑虑却产生了相反的效果。
Due to the lack of scientific proof concerning their impacts, no one has succeeded in winning a lawsuit against cloud-seeding companies.
由于缺乏有关播云影响的科学证据，至今没有人成功打赢针对播云公司的诉讼。
Hence, private climate engineering can proceed in relative legal safety.
因此，私人气候工程可以在法律上相对安全地进行。